## Curriculum Vitae

# Ivan Franco

8130 Avenue de L'Épée, Montreal, QC H3N 2G1 (438) 832-9610

<u>ivan.almeida.franco@gmail.com</u> <u>www.linkedin.com/in/ivan-almeida-franco</u>

# **PROFILE**

10+ years of research, development and strategic management of interactive products and technologies. Clients and partners such as Microsoft, Dell, HP, IBM, Fraunhofer and Philips. Recognized thought-leader in new media art, human-computer interaction and physical interfaces.

## **EXPERTISE**

- R&D manager for award-winning company YDreams.
- Technical, functional and strategic management.
- Intellectual property, licensing and partnerships.
- Team management through Agile principles.
- Worked across teams with Production, Sales, Marketing and VPs.
- Co-inventor of several patents.
- Excellent communicator and consultant.
- Technical skills in HCI, programming, electronic circuitry, product design and rapid prototyping.

# **ACHIEVEMENTS**

- PhD in Music Technology.
- Peer-reviewed publishing and co-author of several patents.
- Business development in Silicon Valley with partners and clients like Dell, HP and IBM.
- Development of AR experiences for Canesta and Primesense, later acquired by Microsoft to create the Kinect controller.
- Guest Speaker at ISE DOOH Business Conference, TEDx, EComm, OFFF, SXSW, ARE, Screenmedia Expo, Berklee College of Music, IBM Research, 6 Sight, NIME, Merging 2011, Pecha Kucha, Future Places, GEAR, Upgrade!, Art Futura, Zeppelin Festival and many universities.
- Participation in IPO operations for YDreams' spin-offs.
- Promotor of the Fab Lab initiative in Portugal, together with Neil Gershenfeld (MIT).

 Winner of several awards and scholarships, including the 2010 Personality of the Year Award by the Portuguese Association for the Promotion of Multimedia and Digital Society.

## WORK EXPERIENCE

2014 - 2019 Researcher and New Media Teacher McGill University

# 2004 - 2013 R&D Director

**YDreams** 

- Management of 25+ researchers and project managers.
- Technical and strategic management of R&D portfolio.
- Intellectual property, licensing and partnerships.
- Financial management of yearly R&D budget of around 1M€.
- Follow-up to product design.

# 2002 - 2004 Associate Researcher

**YDreams** 

- Design and production of audiovisual interactive systems and user interfaces with emphasis on physical computing and realtime processing.
- Creative and strategic consulting.

# 2001 - 2002 Researcher and Teacher

**Pompeu Fabra University** 

- Development of interactive music systems.
- Tutorship in composition and sound production.

# 1997 - 1999 Researcher

**New University of Lisbon** 

• 3D and VR systems applied to GIS and model simulation.

# **EDUCATION**

2014 - 2019	PhD in Music Technology	McGill University
1999 - 2001	M.A. in Digital Arts	Pompeu Fabra University
1993 - 1998	BSc in Environmental Engineering	New University of Lisbon